A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ), Governance and Civil Society, Director, Office Files of Michael Edwards FA596
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ), Governance and Civil Society, Director, Office Files of Michael Edwards
1999-2003
Rockefeller Archive Center
Edwards, Michael ( 1957-)
Ford Foundation
FA596
0.76 Cubic Feet 2 letter document boxes
The Peace and Social Justice Program was established in 1996 to help improve government performance and accountability, foster a thriving independent civil society, and promote human rights. It had two global units: Governance and Civil Society (GCS), and Human Rights. Michael Edwards, a leading expert on civil society, philanthropy and social change with more than two decades of experience working in international relief and development NGOs, served as Director of Governance and Civil Society from 1999 to 2008. The Office Files of Michael Edwards span from 1999 to 2003 and consist of email, memoranda, proposals, meeting agenda books, discussion papers, and reports. The records have been arranged into two series: program management files and meeting files. The program management files contain information about the work of GCS Deputy Director Marcia Smith and Program Officers Julius Ihonvbere and Srilatha Batliwala. These files include email and attachments of papers, proposals and other documents on such topics as GCS initiatives, constitutionalism in Eastern and Central Africa, and transnational civil society. The meeting files hold materials documenting Ford Foundation Officers Meetings and the 2003 GCS Global Meeting in Hanoi, Vietnam.
Biographical / Historical
When Susan Berresford became President of the Foundation in 1996, she established a new program structure consisting of three large thematic programs. Peace and Social Justice was one of these three programs. It was established to help improve government performance and accountability, foster a thriving independent civil society, and promote human rights. It was comprised of two global units: Governance and Civil Society, and Human Rights. In 2009, Peace and Social Justice became the Democracy, Rights and Justice Program.
The Governance and Civil Society unit continued much of the work of the former Governance and Public Policy unit. Its goal, according to the Ford Foundation Annual Report for 1996, was to "stimulate new approaches to designing and implementing public policies, and enhance the role of civic organizations, particularly philanthropies, in promoting democratic values."
Biographical / Historical
Michael Edwards graduated from Oxford University with a B.A. in Geography and received a PhD in Geography from the University of London in 1982. His PhD studies focused on rental housing for the urban poor in Colombia. After leaving academia, he worked with several international relief and development NGOs, including Oxfam (as Regional Director for Southern Africa), Voluntary Service Overseas (as Head of Development Education), Save the Children (as Director of Research, Evaluation and Advocacy), and the World Bank (as Senior Civil Society Specialist).
Dr. Edwards joined the Ford Foundation in 1999 as Director of Governance and Civil Society. He left the Foundation in 2008 to complete visiting fellowships at Demos, New York University's Robert F. Wagner Graduate School of Public Service, and the Brook's World Poverty Institute at Manchester University. An activist, researcher and prolific writer, Dr. Edwards has authored many books and articles on global civil society, philanthropy and social change.
Arrangement
Records are organized into 2 series.
Collection arrangement is as follows:
Series I. Program Management Files, 1999-2002
Series II. Meetings, 2000-2003
Scope and Contents
The Office Files of Michael Edwards span, from 1999 to 2003, his tenure as Director of Governance and Civil Society. The records have been arranged into two series: Program Management and Meetings.
The Program Management files document the work of GCS Deputy Director Marcia Smith and Program Officers Julius Ihonvbere and Srilatha Batliwala. Ms. Smith's files describe several programs and initiatives, including the Collaborations that Count, Fund for Community Organizing, Devolution, and Money and Politics Initiatives as well as annotated drafts of initiative statements. Her files also contain an assessment of her experience managing her portfolio on Civic and Political Participation and her exit memorandum.
Files on Mr. Ihonvbere contain his proposals, work plan, reflection memo, and exit memo relating to the management of his Pluralism and Governance portfolio. Mr. Ihonvbere specialized in the field of constitutionalism. He sought to help nations transitioning from autocracy to democracy with the process of drafting new constitutions. Draft proposals available in his files include one to establish an International Center for Constitutionalism in Lagos, Nigeria. Another proposal requests funds for Mr. Ihonvbere to conduct research, network, and consult for the purpose of building a foundation for establishing a center on constitutionalism. Other files hold reports about his visits to grantees in India, Sri Lanka, the United Kingdom, Nigeria, South Africa, and Zimbabwe. There are also memoranda describing his appointment by Nigerian President Olusegun Obasanjo as Chairperson of the Committee on the Implementation of the Nigerian Bitumen Project in August 2000. In addition, emails describe possible support for the non-governmental organization Justice Africa's human rights and democracy work in Eastern and Central Africa, and the Foundation's policy on regional grants.
The files for Ms. Batliwala contain memoranda regarding a concept paper about building a transnational civil society and email pertaining to a brainstorming meeting on the concept of an NGO virtual university. Other memoranda describe her concern that her portfolio was too unwieldy for a single program officer to manage and the circumstances prompting her request for an extension of her contract and visa. Also available is her extensive exit memo describing the history and evolution of her portfolio on strengthening civil society and the non-profit sector within the U.S. and globally.
The second series in the collection holds materials documenting Ford Foundation Officers Meetings and the 2003 GCS Global Meeting in Hanoi, Vietnam. The files for the Officers Meetings contain detailed agenda with lists of recommended grant actions for consideration. Files for the GCS Global Meeting include the program, resumes for lead speakers, and discussion papers for the workshop, "The Changing State: Structure, Regulation and Sovereignty," held from October 18-20. The GCS meeting files also contain background on the Ford Foundation's programs in Vietnam and China, and statements assessing the fields of Governance and Civil Society.
Separated Materials
Appendix A: Reports – Unpublished reports written by Ford Foundation staff and consultants were removed from their original folders, scanned and transferred to the Archives' collection of staff and consultant reports. See Appendix A for a list of these reports and their specific assigned number. The reports are listed in alphabetical order by author. The assigned number may be used to access reports in the online catalog.
Related Materials
FA592 Ford Foundation records, Peace and Social Justice (PSJ), Governance and Civil Society, Deputy Director, Office Files of Urvashi Vaid. This collection documents her work as a Program Officer (2000) and Deputy Director (2001-2005). The files include documents created by Michael Edwards, Michael Lipsky and June Zeitlin; these predate her tenure with the unit.
FA595 Ford Foundation records, Peace and Social Justice Division (PSJ), Governance and Civil Society, Senior Program Officer, Office Files of Michael Lipsky, 1959-2002, Bulk: 1991-2002. This collection includes correspondence, memoranda, and trip and consultant reports related to two major program initiatives, Innovations in American Government and State Fiscal Analysis Initiative (SFAI). Mr. Lipsky served as Program Officer (1991-1997) and Senior Program Officer (1997-2003) of Governance and Civil Society.
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
- Program Management Files, 1999-2002; I; 0.38 Cubic Feet 1 letter document box
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of communications Dr. Edwards received from his Program Officers, Srilatha Batliwala and Julius Ihonvbere, and from GCS Deputy Director Marcia Smith. The files contain memoranda and email with attachments that include discussion papers, proposals, trip reports, and background documents.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Batliwala, Srilatha -- Exit Memo, 2000 November (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Batliwala, Srilatha -- Re: Brainstorming Meeting on "An NGO Virtual University," Comments on Building a Transnational Civil Society Concept Paper, Visa and Contract Extension, etc., 1999 September-2000 September (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ihonvbere, Julius -- Exit Memo, Reflection Memo on Pluralism and Governance Portfolio, Work Plan for FY 2000-2001, 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Ihonvbere, Julius -- Re: Justice Africa and Regional Grant Policy, Proposals and Papers on Constitutionalism, etc., 1999 October-2002 July (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ihonvbere, Julius -- Re: Trip Reports of Visits to Grantees in India, Sri Lanka, UK, Nigeria, South Africa, Zimbabwe, 1999 October 31-2000 February 7 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Smith, Marcia -- Exit Memo (draft), Attachments (List of Active Grants, Initiative Statement for Fund for Community Organizing, Budget, Departure Letter to Grantees), 2000 October 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Smith, Marcia -- Re: Collaborations That Count Initiative, Fund for Community Organizing Initiative, etc., 2000 February-August (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Smith, Marcia -- Re: Devolution Initiative, Money and Politics Initiative, etc., 1999 November-2000 January (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Meetings, 2000-2003; II; 0.38 Cubic Feet 1 letter document box
  This series consists of files pertaining to Ford Foundation Officers Meetings held between 2000 and 2002, and to a seven day GCS Global Meeting convened in Hanoi, Vietnam in October 2003. The files for the Officers Meetings contain agenda listing recommended grant actions and some official minutes. The GCS Global Meeting files hold background on the Foundation's work in China and Vietnam, including the latter's history with democracy and communal government. The files also hold agendas for meetings and workshops, discussion papers, and field statements.
  - Ford Foundation Officers Meetings -- Agendas Listing Recommended Grant Actions, Some Meeting Minutes ( 1 of 3), 2000 March 6-June 26 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Ford Foundation Officers Meetings -- Agendas Listing Recommended Grant Actions, Some Meeting Minutes (2 of 3), 2000 July 6- 2001 April 26 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Ford Foundation Officers Meetings -- Agendas Listing Recommended Grant Actions, Some Meeting Minutes (3 of 3), 2001 May 10-2002 September 5 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Governance and Civil Society Global Meeting, Hanoi, Vietnam -- Background on Ford Foundation Program in Vietnam, Democracy and Communal Government, etc., 2003 October 18-20 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Governance and Civil Society Global Meeting, Hanoi, Vietnam -- "The Changing State: Structure, Regulation and Sovereignty" Workshop Program, Resume of Lead Speakers, 2003 October 18-20 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Governance and Civil Society Global Meeting, Hanoi, Vietnam -- Discussion Papers, Background Materials, 2003 October 18-20 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Governance and Civil Society Global Meeting, Hanoi, Vietnam -- Agenda, Civil Society Field Statement, Governance Field Statement, 2003 October 22-24 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Governance and Civil Society Global Meeting, Hanoi, Vietnam -- Background on Ford Foundation Grants for Women's Political Participation and International Relations Studies in China, Linkages Between Civil Society and Political Institutions, etc., 2003 October 22-24 (Box 2, Folder 8)